<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<eml:eml xmlns:eml="https://eml.ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.2.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:stmml="http://www.xml-cml.org/schema/stmml-1.2" packageId="1704006b-0a22-4899-a1b3-ebc877bb203c" system="uuid" xsi:schemaLocation="https://eml.ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.2.0 https://eml.ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.2.0/eml.xsd">
  <dataset>
    <shortName>This is the short name</shortName>
    <title>Thresholds and Tipping Points in a Sarracenia Microecosystem at Harvard Forest since 2012</title>
    <creator>
      <individualName>
        <givenName>aaron</givenName>
        <surName>Ellison</surName>
      </individualName>
      <organizationName>Harvard Forest</organizationName>
      <electronicMailAddress>fakeaddress@email.com</electronicMailAddress>
    </creator>
    <pubDate>2012</pubDate>
    <abstract>
      <para>The primary goal of this project is to determine experimentally the amount of lead time 
                               required to prevent a state change. To achieve this goal, we will (1) experimentally induce state
                               changes in a natural aquatic ecosystem - the Sarracenia microecosystem;
                               (2) use proteomic analysis to identify potential indicators of states
                               and state changes; and (3) test whether we can forestall state changes
                               by experimentally intervening in the system. This work uses state-of-the
                               art molecular tools to identify early warning indicators in the field
                               of aerobic to anaerobic state changes driven by nutrient enrichment
                               in an aquatic ecosystem. The study tests two general hypotheses: (1)
                               proteomic biomarkers can function as reliable indicators of impending
                               state changes and may give early warning before increasing variances
                               and statistical flickering of monitored variables; and (2) well-timed
                               intervention based on proteomic biomarkers can avert future state changes
                               in ecological systems.</para>
    </abstract>
    <keywordSet>
      <keyword>Harvard Forest</keyword>
      <keyword>HFR</keyword>
      <keyword>LTER</keyword>
      <keyword>USA</keyword>
      <keywordThesaurus>HFR default</keywordThesaurus>
    </keywordSet>
    <intellectualRights>
      <para>This data package is released to the "public domain" under Creative Commons CC0 1.0 "No Rights Reserved" (see: https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). It is considered professional etiquette to provide attribution of the original work if this data package is shared in whole or by individual components. A generic citation is provided for this data package on the website https://portal.edirepository.org (herein "website") in the summary metadata page. Communication (and collaboration) with the creators of this data package is recommended to prevent duplicate research or publication. This data package (and its components) is made available "as is" and with no warranty of accuracy or fitness for use. The creators of this data package and the website shall not be liable for any damages resulting from misinterpretation or misuse of the data package or its components. Periodic updates of this data package may be available from the website. Thank you.&amp;#13;</para>
    </intellectualRights>
    <licensed>
      <licenseName>Creative Commons Zero v1.0 Universal</licenseName>
      <url>https://spdx.org/licenses/CC0-1.0.html</url>
      <identifier>CC0-1.0</identifier>
    </licensed>
    <coverage>
      <geographicCoverage>
        <geographicDescription>Harvard Forest Greenhouse, Tom Swamp Tract (Harvard Forest)</geographicDescription>
        <boundingCoordinates>
          <westBoundingCoordinate>-122.44</westBoundingCoordinate>
          <eastBoundingCoordinate>-117.15</eastBoundingCoordinate>
          <northBoundingCoordinate>37.38</northBoundingCoordinate>
          <southBoundingCoordinate>30.00</southBoundingCoordinate>
        </boundingCoordinates>
      </geographicCoverage>
      <temporalCoverage>
        <rangeOfDates>
          <beginDate>
            <calendarDate>2012-06-01</calendarDate>
          </beginDate>
          <endDate>
            <calendarDate>2013-12-31</calendarDate>
          </endDate>
        </rangeOfDates>
      </temporalCoverage>
      <taxonomicCoverage>
        <taxonomicClassification>
          <taxonRankName>kingdom</taxonRankName>
          <taxonRankValue>Animalia</taxonRankValue>
          <taxonomicClassification>
            <taxonRankName>phylum</taxonRankName>
            <taxonRankValue>Chordata</taxonRankValue>
            <taxonomicClassification>
              <taxonRankName>class</taxonRankName>
              <taxonRankValue>Teleostei</taxonRankValue>
              <taxonomicClassification>
                <taxonRankName>order</taxonRankName>
                <taxonRankValue>Salmoniformes</taxonRankValue>
                <taxonomicClassification>
                  <taxonRankName>family</taxonRankName>
                  <taxonRankValue>Salmonidae</taxonRankValue>
                  <taxonomicClassification>
                    <taxonRankName>genus</taxonRankName>
                    <taxonRankValue>Oncorhynchus</taxonRankValue>
                    <taxonomicClassification>
                      <taxonRankName>species</taxonRankName>
                      <taxonRankValue>Oncorhynchus tshawytscha</taxonRankValue>
                      <commonName>Chinook Salmon</commonName>
                      <taxonId provider="https://itis.gov">161980</taxonId>
                    </taxonomicClassification>
                  </taxonomicClassification>
                </taxonomicClassification>
              </taxonomicClassification>
            </taxonomicClassification>
          </taxonomicClassification>
        </taxonomicClassification>
      </taxonomicCoverage>
    </coverage>
    <contact>
      <individualName>
        <givenName>aaron</givenName>
        <surName>Ellison</surName>
      </individualName>
      <electronicMailAddress>fakeaddress@email.com</electronicMailAddress>
    </contact>
    <methods>
      <methodStep>
        <description>
          <para>Field methods. All experiments will be carried out in the greenhouse
    at Harvard Forest. We have developed an instrumentation system that
    allows us to collect continuous dissolved [O2] measurements:
    dedicated micro-probes (DO-166MT; Lazar Research Laboratories:
    http://www.shelfscientific.com/) connected to multiplexers and data
    loggers (AM16/32B multiplexer, CR-1000 datalogger and control system
    [Campbell Scientific: http://www.cambellsci.com]). The initial
    ecosystem composition in all experimental plants will be
    standardized by seeding each pitcher with a 10-ml inoculum of liquid
    collected from pitchers growing at Tom Swamp. In all experiments,
    prey will be supplied to pitchers as standardized aliquots of dried
    and finely ground bald-faced hornets (Dolichovespula maculata;
    Hymenoptera: Vespidae), which we collect in quantity throughout New
    England. Both hornets and ants (the latter are the dominant prey of
    S. purpurea) are hymenoptera, and have nearly identical C:N ratios
    (hornets: 3.97; common bog-dwelling ants [Tapinoma sessile and
    Myrmica lobifrons]: 3.37), but on average hornets have greater than
    100 times the dry mass of these ants, and are easier to collect and
    process as a standardized food source. Additions of prey, either as
    large 'pulses' or chronic 'presses' are
    analogous to the enrichment and eutrophication that occur in aquatic
    'green' food webs in which phytoplankton abundance is
    boosted through addition of limiting nutrients. In 'brown'
    food webs such as the Sarracenia microecosystem, detritus - not
    primary production - is at the base of the web, and our treatments
    boost this material as would happen through increases in arthropod
    prey capture78 or through nitrogen-enriched precipitation.</para>
          <para>Proteomic analysis. Proteomic profiles of microbial communities are
    determined after separating the microbial fraction from the pitcher
    fluid, prey, and other detritus. The microbial 'pellet' is
    subjected to SDS-PAGE (sodium dodecyl sulfate polyacrylamide gel)
    electrophoresis; bands are cut out and digested in-gel with trypsin.
    Tryptic peptides are subjected to LC-MS/MS (liquid chromatography
    tandem mass spectrometry) for peptide and protein identification.
    Absolute abundance of peptides and proteins are quantified using
    AQUA (Absolute QUAntification) analysis109.</para>
          <title>General Protocols</title>
        </description>
      </methodStep>
    </methods>
    <methods>
      <methodStep>
        <description>
          <para>Experiment #2. Identification of early intervention time and
    characterization of aerobic and anaerobic proteomes. This experiment
    will use the single enrichment rate E determined from Experiment #1
    and impose different intervention times I at which nutrient
    enrichment will be terminated. Thus, this experiment will identify
    the latest time I* at which it is possible to intervene and stop the
    transition to the anaerobic state by halting enrichment. The [O2]
    profile will again be monitored continuously over 10 days to measure
    the state of the system. From Experiment #1, the transition time T
    to the anaerobic state with no intervention will be known. We will
    use one control group (no prey addition) and ten levels of
    intervention time (all with the same enrichment rate E) as a
    proportion of T (0.1, 0.2, 0.3, 0.4, 0.5, 0.6, 0.7, 0.8, 0.9, 1.0).
    Six plants will be assigned randomly to each of the 11 treatments in
    a randomized one-way layout and [O2] profiles will be monitored
    continuously. In addition to the [O2] profiles, we will also
    characterize the protein profiles of aerobic and anaerobic pitchers
    in all 11 treatment groups at the end of the experiment.</para>
          <para>After the plants are harvested, we will create proteomic profiles of
    the predominantly bacterial portion (centrifuged pellet) of the
    pitcher fluid from each plant, as described in General Protocols.
    Thus, 66 separate pellet-fraction samples will be analyzed by
    SDS-PAGE. After examining the SDS-PAGE profiles, approximately ten
    proteins that show dynamic patterns consistent with state change and
    five that do not change will be cut from the gel, subjected to
    in-gel tryptic digestion and a portion of the tryptic peptides will
    be analyzed by LC-MS/MS. Using these data, we will choose three
    identified peptides from each protein for peptide synthesis such
    that each synthesized peptide contains stable isotope labels (AQUA
    peptides) to distinguish them by mass from the native peptides. We
    will then quantify all 45 of the native peptides from the original
    samples using a known amount of each AQUA peptide spiked into the
    tryptic digest. The AQUA analysis of proteins that do not show
    changes will be used for normalization between samples. These data
    will be used to independently identify the current state of the
    system and forecast the time-to-transition.</para>
          <para>We will use Sequest searches for initial identification of peptides;
    relevant scores including Xcorr and Delta Cn values will be given
    for each peptide. Other peptides will be identified by de novo
    sequencing using PepNovo; all PepNovo scores will likewise be given
    including any N- or C-terminal gaps. Mass error in ppm will be
    reported for each precursor ion. We will use standard multivariate
    analysis to search for distinctive proteomic profiles114 that
    characterize aerobic and anaerobic ecosystems, as well as ecosystems
    that developed with and without inputs of photosynthetic O2 and
    plant metabolites.</para>
          <para>Experiment #3. Identification of diagnostic proteins. Using
    Experiments #1 and 2, we will have identified an enrichment rate E
    with a long pre-tipping period and an intervention time I* before
    which mitigation and termination of enrichment will prevent
    eutrophication. Experiment #3 will characterize the mean and
    variance of the protein profile before and after I*. We are
    especially interested in identifying proteins that increase rapidly
    in abundance (or variance) well before the onset of flickering in
    [O2] and before the transition time T from the aerobic to the
    anaerobic state.</para>
          <para>A cohort of 100 plants all will be fed at rate E (determined from
    Experiment #1), with intervention time I* determined from Experiment
    #2, although no intervention will be used in this 'press'
    experiment so that we can contrast proteins before and after the
    state change. At seven times before I* and three times after
    I<emphasis>, we will harvest 10 randomly chosen plants. At each
    prescribed harvest time, we will measure [O2] and collect samples
    from each plant for proteomic screening using both SDS-PAGE and AQUA
    analysis. This experiment will identify proteins that rise quickly
    in abundance during the pre- I</emphasis> period and can be used as
    early indicators of a future tipping point. Because different plants
    will be harvested at each time period, this is a one-way ANOVA
    design, with pre-and post- I* a priori contrasts. A randomization
    test will be used to determine whether variances in protein
    expression differ through time. During these analyses we will use
    the data from the AQUA peptides and from known amounts of protein
    standards, such as bovine serum albumin, to approximate the amount
    of protein in a given coomassie-stained SDS-PAGE gel band. The
    reason for doing this is to provide a fast 'real-time'
    assay based just on expression in the SDS-PAGE. This rapid assay
    will be used in Experiment #4.</para>
          <para>Experiment # 4. Proof-of-application. This experiment will provide a
    benchmark test of our methods and their ability to correctly
    identify tipping points. A cohort of 100 plants will each be fitted
    with [O2] probes and started on the enrichment regime. Two times per
    day, we will collect 3 plants each, pool their contents, and conduct
    a rapid screen in the lab with SDS-PAGE for the diagnostic proteins
    that were identified in Experiment #3. We will use the protein
    expression in the gel to delineate an 'early' and a
    'late' mitigation strategy. As soon as diagnostic proteins
    measured in the SDS-gels are at abundances that signal we are at
    0.5×I* - approximately one-half of the way to the latest
    intervention time - we will randomly select one third of the
    remaining plants for mitigation and termination of enrichment (the
    'early' mitigation strategy). We will continue to harvest
    plants from the remainder of the cohort and monitor proteins. As
    soon as diagnostic proteins signal we are at 0.75 times I*, we will
    randomly select one half of the remaining plants for mitigation and
    termination of enrichment (the 'late' mitigation
    strategy). The remaining plants (approximately one sixth to one
    third of the original cohort) will continue to be enriched. We will
    monitor [O2] in all 3 groups (no-mitigation control, early
    mitigation, late mitigation) until all plants reach a new [O2]
    equilibrium. If the protein markers are successful, the proportion
    of food webs that remain aerobic will be significantly higher in the
    two mitigation treatments than in the no-mitigation control.</para>
          <title>Specific Experiments</title>
        </description>
      </methodStep>
    </methods>
    <dataTable>
      <entityName>hf205-01-TPexp1.csv</entityName>
      <entityDescription>tipping point experiment 1</entityDescription>
      <physical>
        <objectName>hf205-01-TPexp1.csv</objectName>
        <size unit="bytes">3320</size>
        <authentication method="MD5">899949de36e59e3bd116e2f040061f5a</authentication>
        <dataFormat>
          <textFormat>
            <numHeaderLines>1</numHeaderLines>
            <recordDelimiter>\r\n</recordDelimiter>
            <attributeOrientation>column</attributeOrientation>
            <simpleDelimited>
              <fieldDelimiter>,</fieldDelimiter>
            </simpleDelimited>
          </textFormat>
        </dataFormat>
      </physical>
      <attributeList>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>site_id</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>NA</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>Site id as used in sites table</attributeDefinition>
          <measurementScale>
            <nominal>
              <nonNumericDomain>
                <textDomain>
                  <definition>Site id as used in sites table.</definition>
                  <pattern>NA</pattern>
                </textDomain>
              </nonNumericDomain>
            </nominal>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>hwa</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>NA</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>Hemlock woolly adelgid density per meter of branch</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>decimal</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <ordinal>
              <nonNumericDomain>
                <enumeratedDomain>
                  <codeDefinition>
                    <code>0</code>
                    <definition>0 insects per meter of branch</definition>
                  </codeDefinition>
                  <codeDefinition>
                    <code>1</code>
                    <definition>1-10 insects per meter</definition>
                  </codeDefinition>
                  <codeDefinition>
                    <code>2</code>
                    <definition>11 – 100 insects per meter</definition>
                  </codeDefinition>
                  <codeDefinition>
                    <code>3</code>
                    <definition>more than 100 insects per meter</definition>
                  </codeDefinition>
                </enumeratedDomain>
              </nonNumericDomain>
            </ordinal>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>Count</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>NA</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>Number of individuals observed</attributeDefinition>
          <measurementScale>
            <interval>
              <unit>
                <standardUnit>number</standardUnit>
              </unit>
              <precision>1</precision>
              <numericDomain>
                <numberType>whole</numberType>
                <bounds>
                  <minimum exclusive="false">0</minimum>
                  <maximum exclusive="false">10</maximum>
                </bounds>
              </numericDomain>
            </interval>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>pH</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>NA</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>pH of soil solution</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>float</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <ratio>
              <unit>
                <standardUnit>dimensionless</standardUnit>
              </unit>
              <precision>0.01</precision>
              <numericDomain>
                <numberType>real</numberType>
                <bounds>
                  <minimum exclusive="false">0</minimum>
                  <maximum exclusive="false">14</maximum>
                </bounds>
              </numericDomain>
            </ratio>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>Yrs</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>Years</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>Calendar year of the observation from years 1990 - 2010.</attributeDefinition>
          <measurementScale>
            <dateTime>
              <formatString>YYYY</formatString>
              <dateTimePrecision>1</dateTimePrecision>
              <dateTimeDomain>
                <bounds>
                  <minimum exclusive="false">1993</minimum>
                  <maximum exclusive="false">2003</maximum>
                </bounds>
              </dateTimeDomain>
            </dateTime>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
      </attributeList>
    </dataTable>
  </dataset>
</eml:eml>
